Guide to the Papers of Eliot Freidson 1941-2006 (Bulk 1965-1995) MC 192 MC.192
New York University Archives
Eliot Freidson Papers
1941-2006
1965-1995
New York University Archives
Freidson, Eliot, 1923-2005
MC.192
6 Linear Feet in 18 boxes
This collection consists of the papers of Eliot Freidson, a professor of sociology at New York University from 1961 to 1993. The material consists of files relating to the books he wrote and the courses he taught.
Arrangement
The files are grouped into five series:
I. Correspondence
II. Books (book titles as subseries)
III. Course Materials
IV. Subject Files
V. Articles
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of Eliot Freidson's files relating to the books he wrote and published and the courses he taught. Approximately two linear feet of the collection consist of copies of journal articles on topics relating to his research. The "Books" series consists mostly of correspondence with publishers and colleagues who read chapter drafts and offered critiques. The "Course Materials" series consists of syllabi, lecture notes and outlines. Subject files contain speeches, obituaries, and conference materials.
Historical/Biographical Note
Eliot Freidson (pronounced "fried-son") was born in Boston on February 20, 1923, to Joseph and Grace Backer Freidson, both of whom emigrated from Russia as children. He attended the University of Maine for one year in 1941, transferring to the University of Chicago in 1942. He served in the U.S. Army from April 1943 to July 1946 in Europe as a translator of German and intelligence analyst. Freidson earned his Ph.D. in sociology from the University of Chicago in 1952. He taught first at the City College of New York before becoming an associate professor at NYU in 1961 and achieving full professorship in 1964. Freidson served as chair of the Department of Sociology from 1975 to 1978. He retired in 1993 and was a professor emeritus at NYU until his death. He served as president of the Eastern Sociological Society from 1985 to 1986. He died on December 14, 2005 of non-Hodgkins lymphoma in San Francisco.
Freidson studied the sociology of professions and was most widely recognized for his studies of the medical field. He wrote 12 books and over 100 scholarly articles.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Freidson's wife, Helen Giambruni, in 2006 and 2017.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Eastern Sociological Society (U.S.); Giddens, Anthony
- Series I: Correspondence, 82913
  - Correspondence, 1 of 5, 1951-1969; 82917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2 of 5, 1970-1976; 82916 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 3 of 5, 1977-1982; 82915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 4 of 5, 1982-1987; 82914 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 5 of 5, 1987-2004; 82912 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Books, 82850
  - Subseries I: Doctoring Together, 82905
    - Correspondence, 1974-1975; 82911 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1976-1977; 82910 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1978-1981; 82909 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1990; 82908 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Reviews and Promotional Material, 1976-1981; 82907 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Memos, Royalty Statement, List, 1975-1978; 82906 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subseries II: The Fate of Knowledge, 82895
    - Correspondence, 1985; 82904 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1986; 82903 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1987; 82902 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1989-1991; 82901 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1992; 82900 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1993; 82899 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Review and Promotional Material, 1986-1987; 82898 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Notes, 1985; 82897 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Notes, Drafts, etc, 1986-1992; 82896 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Subseries III: Medical Men and Their Work, 82890
    - Correspondence, 1967-1977; 82894 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1968-1971; 82893 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Notes and Promotional Material, 1970-1974; 82892 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Royalties, 1970-1980; 82891 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Subseries IV: Medical Work in America, 82888
    - Reviews and Promotional Material, 1989-1990; 82889 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Subseries V: Profession of Medicine, 82880
    - Correspondence, 1961-1968; 82887 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1963-1969; 82886 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1969-1977; 82885 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1978-1988; 82884 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Reviews and Promotional Materials, 1968-1989; 82883 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Documents, 1962-1988; 82882 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Notes and Comments, 1961-1981; 82881 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Subseries VI: Professions and Their Prospects, 82875
    - Correspondence, 1970; 82879 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1971; 82878 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1979; 82877 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Publication Material, 1971-1979; 82876 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Subseries VII: Professional Dominance, 82871
    - Correspondence, 1969-1990; 82874 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Reviews and Promotional Material, 1971; 82873 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Royalties, 1974-1986; 82872 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Subseries VIII: Professional Ethics, 82869
    - Notes, undated; 82870 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Subseries IX: Professional Powers, 82862
    - Correspondence, 1983-1984; 82868 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1985; 82867 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1986-1988; 82866 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Reviews and Promotional Materials, 1986-1989; 82865 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Notes, Drafts, Etc, 1981-1989; 82864 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Lecture Notes, 82863 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Subseries X: Professsionalism: The Third Logic, 82858
    - Correspondence, 1995-1999; 82861 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Notes, ca. 1995-1999; 82860 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Drafts, ca. 1995-1999; 82859 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Subseries XI: Professionalism Reborn, 82851
    - Correspondence, 1987-1992; 82857 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1993; 82856 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, Aug-93, Dec-93; 82855 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1994-1996; 82854 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Reviews and Promotional Materials, 1994-1995; 82853 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Drafts, 1987-1992; 82852 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Series III: Course Materials, 82828
  - Deviance, 1966-1970; 82849 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Field Methods, 1 of 4, 1982-1992; 82848 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Field Methods, 2 of 4, 1980-1992; 82847 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Field Methods, 3 of 4, 1961-1982; 82846 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Field Methods, 4 of 4, 1970-1988; 82845 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Industrial Sociology, 1967-1974; 82844 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Occupations and Professions, 1 of 4, 1991-1992; 82843 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Occupations and Professions, 2 of 4, 1992; 82842 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Occupations and Professions, 3 of 4, 1962-1987; 82841 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Occupations and Professions, 4 of 4, 1972-1992; 82840 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Occupations and Professions [Graduate], 1 of 2, 1958-1988; 82839 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Occupations and Professions [Graduate], 2 of 2, 1981-1992; 82838 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Organizations, 1965-1972; 82837 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Social Communication, 1953-1963; 82836 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Sociology of Knowledge, 1 of 2, 1971-1973; 82835 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Sociology of Knowledge, 2 of 2, 1971-1972; 82834 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Sociology of the Legal Profession, 1989-1990; 82833 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Sociology of the Medicine, 1 of 3, 1959-1975; 82832 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Sociology of the Medicine, 2 of 3, 1969-1974; 82831 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Sociology of the Medicine, 3 of 3, 1961-1962; 82830 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Sociology of New York Performance, 1985-1987; 82829 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Series IV: Subject Files, 82810
  - Department of Sociology Business, 1976-1988; 82827 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Eastern Sociological Society, 1986; 82826 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Manuscripts, 1 of 3, 1955-1959; 82825 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Manuscripts, 2 of 3, 1957-1962; 82824 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Manuscripts, 3 of 3, 1947-1977; 82823 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Obituaries and Memorial Articles, 2006; 82822 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Personal [Army Records], 1941-1953; 82821 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Retirement, etc, 1993-1998; 82820 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Speeches, Misc., 1 of 5, 1967-1999; 82819 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Speeches, Misc., 2 of 5, 1969-1991; 82818 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Speeches, Misc., 3 of 5, 1972-1980; 82817 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Speeches, Misc., 4 of 5, 1975-1986; 82816 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Speeches, Misc., 5 of 5, 1978-1982; 82815 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Talks and Lectures, 1 of 2, 1980-1987; 82814 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Talks and Lectures, 2 of 2, 1988-1992; 82813 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Translations of Poetry, undated; 82812 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - University of Chicago Papers, 1948-1949; 82811 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - 3.5 inch floppy discs, entitled "Theory of Professionalism, 5/95" and "Fate of Knowledge, 5/95 + endnotes", 1995; 170989 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Series V: Articles, 82759
  - A, 1981-1991; 82809 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - B, 1983-1996; 82808 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - C, 1983-1986; 82807 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - D, 1982; 82806 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - E, 1982-2000; 82805 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - F, 1980-1993; 82804 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - G, 1979-1988; 82803 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - H, 1999-2000; 82802 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - J, 1984; 82801 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - K, 1985-1999; 82800 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - L, 1972-1992; 82799 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - M, 1987-1999; 82798 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - N, 2000; 82797 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - O, 1978-1992; 82796 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - P, 1993-1994; 82795 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - R, 1988; 82794 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - S, 82793 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - T, 1987-1995; 82792 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - V, 1984; 82791 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - W, 1917-1995; 82790 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - XYZ, 1980-1993; 82789 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Articles and Books of Interest, 1979-1982; 82788 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Articles and Books of Interest, 1986-1990; 82787 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Articles and Books of Interest, 1986-1995; 82786 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Articles and Books of Interest, 1993-2001; 82785 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Ethical Codes, 1988-1995; 82784 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - The Fate of Knowledge, Source Material, France, 1972-1991; 82783 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - The Fate of Knowledge, Source Material, France, 1983; 82782 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - The Fate of Knowledge, Source Material, Germany, 82781 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - The Fate of Knowledge, Source Material, Russia, 1993; 82780 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - The Fate of Knowledge, Source Material, United Kingdom, 82779 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - The Fate of Knowledge, Source Material, United Kingdom, 1980-1993; 82778 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - The Fate of Knowledge, Source Material, United States, 1982-1986; 82777 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - The Fate of Knowledge, Source Material, Comparative, 1985-1992; 82776 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Intellectual Property, 1 of 3, 1972-2002; 82775 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Intellectual Property, 2 of 3, 1984-1993; 82774 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Intellectual Property, 3 of 3, 1982-1990; 82773 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Professional Ethics, 1888-1995; 82772 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Professional Ethics, 1957-1997; 82771 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Professionalism: The Third Logic, 1964-1991; 82770 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Professionalism: The Third Logic, 1971-1986; 82769 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Professionalism: The Third Logic, 1974-1990; 82768 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Professionalism: The Third Logic, 1972-1992; 82767 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Reprint Journals, undated; 82766 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Reprint Journals, 1953-1958; 82765 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Reprint Journals, 1960-1968; 82764 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Reprint Journals, 1970-1979; 82763 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Reprint Journals, 1981-1985; 82762 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Reprint Journals, 1986-1989; 82761 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Reprint Journals, 1992-2002; 82760 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Series VI: Published Materials, 170980
  - "Physicians in Large Medical Groups: A Preliminary Report", with Buford Rhea, in "Medical Care Research", ed. K.L. White, 1965; 170981 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Notes by Freidson in "Essays on the New Working Class" by Serge Mallet, trans. Dick Howard and Dean Savage, 1975; 170982 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - "Response: Societal Commitment to Equity: Role of the Medical Care Provider", in "Implications of Guaranteeing Medical Care: Papers and Commentary from Annual Meeting", National Academy of Sciences, ed. Joseph G. Peprich (includes note), 1975; 170983 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - "Rechtsschutz fur Sozialforschung - Kriterien zum Definition", in "Forschung in Konflikt mit Recht und Ethik", eds. Albin Eser and Karl F. Schumann, 1976; 170984 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - "Relations between Physicians in an Organized Form of Practice", in "Sante, Medecine et Sociologie", Colloque International de Sociologie Medical (portions drawn from book "Doctoring Together", 1976), 1978; 170985 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - "Nourishing Professionalism", in "Ethics, Trust, and the Professions: Philosophical and Cultural Aspects", eds. E. Pellegrino, R. Veatch, and J. Langan, 1991; 170986 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - "Professionalism: The Third Logic", by Eliot Freidson, Korean translation, 2007; 170987 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Journal of Health Politics, Policy, and Law, Volume 28, Number 1, February 2003 (Special Book Review Symposium: Eliot Freidson's "Professionalism: The Third Logic"), 170988 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Medical Professionals and the Organization of Knowledge (English and Translations), 2009 (Box 19, Folder 1-3)